Hello, everyone. Yeah, so now this is the rest of my demo of the automation. So the first part, we did the simplification, right?
Simplification, and
discussed a few things about it and tried it on some example. I actually forgot to say just one more syntax related to the simplification,
which is that
if you want
to use,
if you want to remove all facts,
except remove all facts
for all simp rules from
the simp set,
except a specific fact or a specific number of facts, let's say specific fact F1.
You can use, you can use apply
simp only
F1. So that means that the simp set now is only F1. You can also add a sequence of facts instead of F1, F1, F2, etc.
So that's the last thing about the simplification that I wanted to
mention. Perhaps also there is something else that I mentioned briefly, but maybe I can just discuss it with you a bit more.
So the simplification here,
this is a conditional simplification rule. So it again has the same form where it's a substitution,
but the simplifier will actually try to apply it,
like if you give this to the simplifier as a simplification rule, it will try to apply it.
And what does that mean? It will try to first see if that assumption holds and if it doesn't hold, then it won't apply it.
And it will try to prove this assumption, but
of course it's not guaranteed to be able to prove it. But I just wanted to mention that
thing about conditional simplification rules.
Okay, so the second thing,
so now we did simplification. The second thing, the second kind of
automation that I want to discuss is
the so-called auto.
So basically that's the most
used form of automation in Isabelle for simple projects at least.
So what does auto do? Auto is roughly
simplification plus
forward and
backward reasoning.
Well, let me just say it a different way. It's a simplification plus
something called classical
reasoning, okay?
What is classical reasoning? It is
in the same way simplification
is
repetitive
substitution, right? repetitive attempts of substitution.
Classical reasoning is
repetitive
forward
and backward
reasoning.
And this is very important. This gives it much more power than just simplification, but it also makes it
even less complete.
So in the sense that it doesn't have any theoretical guarantees
in terms of termination and running time.
So again,
so auto uses, let me just say some theoretical features of it, so uses
the same
sim set
as prove the handwriting a bit,
the simplifier,
okay?
and also
has
its own
bank
of
forward
and backward
reasoning
lemmas. So lemmas that
are used for forward and backward reasoning.
And, um, let me just see if there is something that I forgot about it before I...
Yeah, so let me just say so so like something I'll do it theoretically here, but then I'll just tell you. So recall
that to extend
the
sim set for simp
for the proof method simp
just write it more clearly
we used
simp
add
or we use also delete
or only
some fact some rule one some simp one
so
that's
rule one simp rule one rule two
etc. Okay
you can use we can use
the same
to up to
change
the simplification
rules
used
by
auto.
Okay, um also importantly, um
to change to add
or remove
a lemma to the backward
to the classical reasoning we do the following.
So you can you can say
apply
auto
intro
fact
one
that declares
that adds fact one to the backward reasoning, um
to the
backward reasoning
um
lemmas and if you say apply
auto
dest
fact one that again adds
fact
one to the
forward reasoning lemmas and recall that I said
backward
reasoning
is
yeah, sorry forward reasoning is preferable in
when we're doing pen and paper proofs because that's how I do it at least and how a lot of you I suppose do the
proofs you start from assumptions and go towards conclusions because our reasoning is
was
is
preferable
for
manual
reasoning
for automation
backward reasoning
is
preferable
because
it can
if you remember how backward reasoning worked, um
if you have a goal p for example
p and q let's say and then you want to
like one backward reasoning step would be
uh well one backward reasoning lemma would be the lemma that says
p
if you have p separately and q separately then you can derive p and q
if you apply that lemma
to this
and with a backward reasoning approach then you will have instead of that goal
if you apply that
as a backward reasoning so
if you remember a course called rule
the new goal you have two new goals goal one
and goal two the first goal is p the second goal is q and then it it helps you basically analyze things automatically
so that then you can prove that manually and that manually
that's why backward reasoning is preferable for automation. So, um because it helps you
um
better
with debugging
that's because you usually
are more confident about what you want to prove rather like the conclusion you are usually
usually
are
more
confident
um
about
the conclusion
you want
to derive
right
um
and
rather than assumptions. So usually the way it goes is that
you start from the conclusion
figure out
the
assumptions
using
backward
reasoning
okay
so that's I think the the mainly the theory for this
section
uh for for this for auto at least
um
so let's try it on on an example on on the same example
and then I'll have a few more uh things to say about automation
so um
so let's say
um
I'll just try it in the same example that we had there
So so remember that's the proof that we tried with simp. So
So auto is usually more powerful because it has simplification plus classical reasoning as you can see so you can of course do the everything with auto
um
but but if you remember simplification failed
to um
Do the case splitting on its own right? Because if I if we do the following if we do using cons
Got ih and cons of two
and then apply
simp
That failed you'd see it didn't finish the goal and it helped a bit with it, but it didn't finish it
uh, but
If you do auto it can actually finish the goal so you can just do it like that
so then you have um
The same thing by auto and then you can let me just copy that so that we have that simp version as well
I'll just copy the same same proof and then finish it with auto. So
here we have um
lemma
X is in that and you can just say by auto
and here you say
by auto
and
By auto, I finished all the goals and then i'll just try and serve doing the case splitting manually
I'll just try to use all the facts that i'm using in all the cases. I'll just add them here
and try auto
Yeah, and as you can see it finishes it
So then in this case like like when when one proof method finishes all the sub cases
Especially when auto finishes all the sub cases what you can do is then try to
Instead of splitting them manually you can just do it
Um, you can do it shorter in a shorter way
So i'll just try and do this in a shorter way, but leave leave the above proof as well
So you can also do it instead of so here we're doing induction and then doing two cases separately, but if but because
um
Okay. So first of all, are you use them here instead of adding these
These facts manually so we just have
When you say then then you have them added
Okay, and but then instead of uh doing this proof manually like that we can also try something else which is
Apply induction
and then um
You can apply auto
To each of the subgoals. So we look here we had so actually there's an important thing difference between both, uh things
Um between both but auto and simp. I'll just write it to the
to that
um here
so
um
note
auto
applies
to all
open goals
This is unlike simp
this is unlike
All the methods that i've shown you so unlike
simp
or subst
or
rule
Auto applies to all open goals. So going back to isabelle
when you apply when you applied
induction
Here we have that that's a method. That's the proof method that gave you two sub goals two new goals, right the base case
and the step the step case and then you can
um
If you just apply auto here
It will solve both, right?
So because as i said auto applies itself to each of the sub goals and since auto could solve the first sub goal and the second
Some goal then it could solve the whole thing
So you can just um, you can also do it that way
You can then do done or you can then do dot
And that's the same. So that's uh, that's an that's an example of auto
Let me try to
Do another example of auto
using
the previous
examples of um
Over the backward reasoning
so i'll go back to the first week
and
Let me just see
Or case analysis like that was a completely complicated example, right? Um, so let me just copy that to the
To the automation
To the dimension file
Let's just copy that proof if you remember that proof
We needed to prove that x minus y is smaller than or equal to x and then you had to
Do that by induction on the natural number and then split cases
And then we needed to prove this lemma
Also, so I will just try and do that with auto to show you the power of that method
So first of all, we need to show that if a is less than b then suck a is less than suck b
So I will just try and do that
by
induction and auto
Induction on a let's say and then apply auto and see where it goes
Okay, so as you can see that's finished then now we have to prove this lemma
instead of having um
Instead of having to say instead of having these steps because as I said if you remember I said that uh auto
and simple have
A lot of theorems in the report in in in the bank of simplification and forward and backward reasoning
So here we have zero diff and order refle
There are two theorems that we're using so let's just
Try and do that by auto so
instead of
so we can say
Auto, yeah, and it works again
and then here we have
You have a split splitting a case you have the case where x is greater than or equal to y and
you have the case when
X is smaller than y. So let's just try to do the whole thing by auto. So I would just say
then
Show that so then i'm including here the induction hypothesis
It's the induction hypothesis and that's the goal
So that's um
Try and do that by auto and see if it will finish it
Yeah, it could finish it. So as you can see it can do a lot of reasoning
And makes many many proofs
significantly shorter
so then um
but a lot of the times
You have to understand why this why why a certain
Theorem holds in order for you to be able to debug it. I mean you can use auto
to to just
Make some progress with the goal
And then you will have something remaining
like like
Like this for example, and then you can analyze what's there and then know what lemmas you need to prove
And then provide to auto in order for auto to to finish the goal. That's the usual workflow
I mean we will do that a lot more in the large repository and also
In the lab you will do that
so induction
on x
then apply
auto
Then the same
So that's another thing that you can prove with auto and we didn't even need lemma 4 as you can see
Because it has an equivalent of lemma 4 or something that can lead to lemma 4 in its uh bank
So let's try another example
um, so let me just
um
Yeah, let's try another example
Again from week one
I think this was the most complicated example
Um the case analysis one had all the features of backward and forward reasoning
um
Let me just try and show you how you add something
To the backward and forward reasoning. So here for example
In this example, we're using auto user. So if you remember we used
We were using cons ih and cons 2 so cons ih the induction hypothesis actually can be used
either as a backward reasoning step where you where you look for that in the conclusion and then
Remove it and add that to that and make that turn that into the conclusion instead
Or you can use this forward where you if you have that assumption
Then you can take that assumption
If you if you have that assumption in your goal
then then you would
Then then then the forward reasoning
Which which we would do on pen and paper would would say okay
Remove that assumption and get that inclusion
Because you would instantiate that assumption with what with with the one that you have
Um here you can do this
Automatically, I would just add the induction hypothesis and see
If it works as forward or backward reasoning step or no as a forward or backward reasoning step or no
So let's just do this is a forward reasoning step
So it works as you can see
And also if we do it as a backward reasoning step
It would now it didn't work. So
Why?
Let's see
So what are we left with?
x is
so what was
The original goal is that max x is less than max list. So when you did this auto did a lot of
simplification
um
And said that okay x x it said that it was able to find out using the simplification rules that come from the definition max list
That x less than that thing is the same as
X
Less than the maximum of a and the max list of the rest
So it didn't actually apply the induction hypothesis at all
Yeah, because why is that that actually makes sense because let's just look into the induction hypothesis
And compare it to that goal
Let's see. So you have x is smaller than
max list
right
So you didn't but but you don't have that in the goal
So you cannot go backwards from it because backward reasoning goes by taking the conclusion
and seeing if it occurs there and then
replacing
that
Like like if this conclusion occurs in the goal then it replaces that conclusion with another goal
Which is the assumption of the theorem that using backward reasoning and that's why the backward reasoning here didn't work
But why did it work as forward reasoning because the assumption?
here
So forward reasoning again
If you remember forward reasoning work as follows you have a theorem that has an assumption and a conclusion
And then if you have the assumption you can instantiate
If you have the assumption in your in your list of available facts
Then you can instantiate the assumption of that theorem and then get the conclusion as an as a new fact without the assumption
So here was able to do that because we have
that assumption
There in our goal
So it was able to do forward reasoning by taking that assumption and instantiating
instantiating this
The induction hypothesis with that assumption. So then you have
You just have the conclusion without any assumption and then you replaced it with the conclusion and then it has
inside of it a lemma that allowed it to
To realise that x is
smaller than or equal
max of a and max of list max list of prime
max prime of x's
It was able to
It probably has a lemma that says that if x is smaller than or equal to one of the two arguments of max
Then it's smaller than or equal to the max
so if we um
So maybe let's just try and do that so that I can show you the backward reasoning
So I said that the lemma that it must have used is the following it's a lemma that says max
and
if x
x is a natural
less than
e
and that implies that
x
Is less than maximum of a and b for any a right?
So it already has that so that's exactly what I meant. So it has max co-bounded i2
So it used it. So so if you want to do it with backward reasoning, you can firstly do backward reasoning with that
and then
So let's just do that first
Was it max co-bounded I think yeah
Um, but it didn't do it you sometimes need to add this bang actually in order for it in order for you to force it
um
to do what um
What you wanted to do?
No, so so I think it it used
You know, that was the wrong conclusion. So I don't know like yeah, we need to debug this a little more
I think let's do that in the in the large group tutorial if you want
But the point is yeah applying cons the induction hypothesis backward reasoning didn't work because you need to apply something before it
um
Like in order for you to use this as a backward reasoning rule you need to apply
first
That gets rid of basically gets rid of the max a so that so that then the goal
Matches the conclusion of your backward reasoning rule and then you can do backward reasoning and replace the goal with the assumption
okay
so, um
I think that's
An example of of of um
Of auto
Okay
So, uh, maybe that one last thing which is just a notation thing or you know, it's a it's um
Like a notation thing that that we need to do. Um
So so when you prove a lemma
So notation some notate some notes on notation and isabelle so when you prove a lemma
let's say
lemma lemma one
For example, I don't know no one
x plus y equals y plus x
And you always want and you always want it and you want to add it to the sim set
And so you basically want
It to always be used for simplification by default
You can declare it as a simple by doing the following so you can say lemma one
Simp, uh, you can do the same thing for forward and backward reasoning
by declaring it um
um
For forward or backward reasoning
You can declare it as uh, you can you can do lemma one
So for forward you can say dest rule and for backward you can say
Uh intro rule
And then this will always be
Um used by default by auto or simp
Okay
So, um, let me just discuss briefly two other proof methods
so there is another proof method called
um
force and fastforce
This also is very important. I think
These are
like more powerful than auto
but
they
cannot
stop
in the middle
Like auto or simp, so they're not very good. So not good for debugging
um
But otherwise they have the same that they like they can they they use the same they use the same
Um
Use the same thing. They use the same simp sets. Let me just so they use
simps
intro
And destruction rules the same way for backward and forward and simplification and substitution
Um, so not good for debugging. That's one one thing
also another difference between
fastforce and auto
unlike auto
they only
apply
to one
To the first sub goal to the first goal
If you have a list of goals that's open they only apply
to the
first
goal
so I think that's um
So that's it for for auto and force. So let me just
go with you through the
Examples again show you how we can use fastforce. I mean it's the same
For example, let me just copy that one
Or maybe let me copy that one
Um, because that one would show us the difference between
So let me just divide that file
so here
multiplication
and then this is
auto
And then let's let's do here
I'll just do fastforce
So fastforce is slightly faster than force, but yeah
So we have dual induction on x's and then you have two cases two goals. So the first is that
And the base case and the second is the sub case. So if I just apply force there
If you see before force we had two sub goals after force it only
Sold the first goal because as I said it applies itself to the first goal
So then you can apply it again to the second goal
And then it's done
So the same for fastforce
Okay
So that's for fastforce and for force
So before I close I would also like to just add one more note
in the in the thing in the
Blackboard
So here another note is the following which is that
To deal with different categories of goals
There are
three
defined
sets of
simps
for example
um
So so I won't go into the depth here
I'll just give you an example, but these are we should just see that if we if we come across any example
So for example, we have
algebra
simps
These from their names. They have like a lot of algebraic reasoning
Simplification rules and then we have like field simps
So this is this can use and this is this can use this can be used to
Reason about fields. So so for example, if you have a division or something like that
So that's one thing I wanted to say
um
Um a very important example is natural numbers
is natural numbers
To deal with those in general. If you remember I said that there is um
like the like natural numbers
Uh, like like natural numbers can be represented as suck something. So to translate between
for example
suck
a or suck suck a and two which are equivalent
Sucks like not an a plus two not a plus two, but I would just say and um, maybe yeah a plus two and
a plus two
we can use
we use um
something called um
eval
net
numerals
so this this is why is it called that because um
This is a numeral
And this is a natural number and the numerals said as I said are are overloaded between different
Type of numbers national numbers real numbers, etc
And these are just natural numbers. So eval eval net numeral, that's pretty important if you want to reason about
Goals that have numerals in them. So all of these are
I'm trying to list some hints
But I think the best way to do that is by doing examples on your own or with us
Or with me in the or like before we do the large group tutorial or also in the lab
It's all of the but but i'm trying to list as many notes as possible
um
So that's all um
Thank you very much and I hope um
That was enjoyable